Hey בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody, we start a new מסכת masechet
today, we start a new סדר seder today, we move from נזיקין
Nezikin to קדשים, Kodshim, and we start with זבחים, Zevachim, which is
a large מסכת, masechet, about 120 דף, daf, it's gonna last us
for four months, after זבחים Zevachim there's gonna be מנחות, Menachot, זבחים
Zevachim is about the animal sacrifices, מנחות Menachot are about the grain
sacrifices, and then both of those two מסכתות masechtos there are well
there's you know there's a standard תוספות, Tosafos, if you from הוריות
Horiyos you know remember we didn't even have like a real תוספות,
Tosafos, but or like a significant one, so in both those מסכתות
masechtos you have you know major רש''י תוספות Rashi Tosafos and so
on, but you don't really have the other ראשונים, Rishonim, the third
מסכת masechet we're gonna get to in this is חולין, Chullin, although
known by the ראשונים Rishonim as שחיטת חולין, Shechitat Chullin, which is
the slaughtering of non-קדשים Kodshim animals as opposed to ours which is
about the slaughtering of קדשים Kodshim animals, and that's gonna be about
all the classic laws of כשרות kashrut of meat, so that's where
you have a lot a lot of ראשונים, Rishonim, but this מסכת
masechet and these two there's very little, you know in general for
קדשים Kodshim very little ראשונים, Rishonim, of course there is a רמב''ם
Rambam and ראב''ד Ra'avad etc., there's also no ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, we've never
had a ירושלמי Yerushalmi on קדשים, Kodshim, although רמב''ם Rambam in his
פירוש המשניות Peirush Hamishnayot says that there's a ירושלמי Yerushalmi on קדשים,
Kodshim, and about 150 years ago or so somebody says they discovered
a ירושלמי Yerushalmi in קדשים, Kodshim, but it turned out to be
a forgery, so anyway so we basically have the גמרא Gemara and
רש''י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafos we skipped
עדיות Eduyos right?
There's no גמרא Gemara on עדיות, Eduyos, so the דף יומי Daf
Yomi does not do עדיות, Eduyos, also the דף יומי Daf Yomi
does not do אבות, Avos, okay so here we go let's get
started, כל הזבחים שנזבחו שלא לשמן כשרים, Kol hazevachim shenizbechu shelo lishman
kesherim, all the sacrifices that are slaughtered, I mean זבח
zevach can just mean something that was slaughtered, זבחת ואכלת במקום, zavachtah
ve'achaltah bamakom, but anyway תזבח, tizbach, but here it specifically means here
you know animal animals that are slaughtered for sacrifice, all the animals
that were slaughtered שלא לשמן, shelo lishman, not for their name, meaning
not for the type of sacrifice they are, the חטאת, chatat, אשם,
asham, עולה, olah, שלמים, shelamim, you know, so when you slaughtered it
you thought, because remember the כהנים kohanim are slaughtering it, it doesn't
have to be actually, slaughtering is the one עבודה, avodah, the one
act of service in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash that can be
done by a non-כהן, kohen, but by default it was done by
the כהנים kohanim regardless, it wasn't done by the owners, so there
they are you imagine got thousands of people like they have a
number system, 237, next, you know whatever, but anyway you got all
these people bringing their sacrifices,
you might want to start putting like labels on the sacrifice or
hanging little necklaces around their necks, but anyway you could imagine that
the כהן kohen gets confused about you know whose animal this is,
what type of a sacrifice this is, so if it was slaughtered
שלא לשמן shelo lishman with the wrong type of sacrifice in mind,
it was an עולה olah it was slaughtered for שלמים shelamim or
vice versa, כשרים, kesherim, the sacrifice is still valid אלא שלא עלו
לבעלים לשם חובה, ela shelo alu leba'alim lesheim chovah, but it does
not go up, it was not offered for their owners to satisfy
their obligation, so this makes an important distinction right at the beginning
that you know what it means for a sacrifice to be a
כשר kasher is not a question about whether the owner satisfied his
obligation, the owner can have an obligation to bring sacrifices for a
number of reasons, one is he did a sin he has to
bring a חטאת, chatat, or if it's a certain type of a
thing like part of a טהרה taharah process, a woman who gives
birth often will also bring a חטאת chatat or maybe sometimes an
עולה olah and so on, so you have to bring it because
of sin, you have to bring it as part of a purification
process, or you bring it because you accepted a vow upon yourself,
somebody said I accept upon myself an obligation to bring an עולה,
olah, to bring a שלמים, shelamim, okay other case קרבן פסח, korban
pesach, anyway a lot of reasons why you might want to bring
a sacrifice, sometimes you can
be obligated to bring a
sacrifice, sometimes you can bring a sacrifice without any personal obligation, how
would that be? I wanted to bring an עולה, olah, I'm not
obligated to it, and rather than saying I hereby obligate myself I
just sanctified this animal as an עולה olah and I brought it
to the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, and here's a sacrifice and I'm
not, if it gets lost something happens to it I'm not obligated,
I don't have a personal obligation, so there's a big difference between
the sense of a personal obligation and the animal qua sacrifice, now
if something is significantly done wrong with the animal then it is
an invalid sacrifice, and that means that you don't bring it, you
don't sprinkle the blood on the מזבח, mizbeach, you don't burn the
fats on the
מזבח, mizbeach, the כהנים kohanim don't eat the meat, the owners don't
eat the meat, it has to be burned you know and so
on, if it is a כשר kosher sacrifice then that means you
go through the rest of the procedures correctly and you know if
it's a type of thing that the כהנים kohanim eat the meat,
the owners eat the meat, you do all the things you're supposed
to do, but the saying that the object, the animal as an
animal is a כשר kosher sacrifice is not saying that the owner
fulfilled his obligation, and here what we say is that when the
כהן kohen has the wrong thing in mind when he slaughters it
and we're gonna find out in
the
גמרא... Gemara... If the owner goes ahead and I mean so if
the if any of those acts are done within the mind is
a different sacrifice, that somehow, you know, sort of severs the connection
to the owner or puts it off its course enough that it
doesn't change the status of the sacrifice as a כשר kosher sacrifice,
but it means the owner is no longer satisfying his obligation, if
he has an obligation. So he would then have to bring another
one. He would for חטאת chatat or for פסח Pesach or for
you know whatever the case might be. Okay. He would have to
bring another sacrifice but the sacrifice as a sacrifice is כשר. kosher.
Why isn't the כהן kohen held responsible?
So that's a different question. That's actually a נזיקין nezikin question, which
is that if the כהן kohen does this and therefore causes the
owner a loss, does he have to pay compensation to the owner?
And that's basically a whole discussion, I mean the גמרא Gemara in
גיטין Gittin actually surprisingly anyway discusses it and some of it has
to do with is the כהן kohen intentional or not intentional.
If the כהן kohen intentionally does it then he then he does
have to pay. If he doesn't intentionally do it he doesn't. The
question is like what's the real rule? Is the real rule he
never has to pay but we're making him pay when he's intentional
or is the real rule that he always has to pay but
we're getting him off when he's unintentional because otherwise who's going to
do the, you know, they're going to be obviously I mean they
they don't have much of a choice but obviously, you know, they're
not going to be so thrilled about having to do it if
they're going to have all this חיוב chiyuv liability and so on.
Right? So anyway. Okay. So but yes, that's good question. But that's
like a different הלכה halacha discussion. Okay. אלא שלא עלו לבעלים לשם
חובה. ella shelo alu l'be'alim l'shem chova. חוץ מן הפסח והחטאת. chutz
min haPesach v'haChatat. The one the two exceptions to this rule that
the animal actually becomes invalid as a sacrifice is a sin offering
and a פסח, Pesach, or פסח Pesach and a sin offering. הפסח
בזמנו, haPesach bizmano, פסח Pesach during the time you're supposed to bring
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach from the midday on the 14th until
nightfall. That's when a פסח Pesach is כשר. kasher. So if you
bring a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, an animal you sanctified as a
פסח Pesach and you bring it the other the remainder of the
364 and a half days out of the year, so then automatically
it becomes a שלמים. shelamim. Okay. And therefore so it doesn't follow
the rules of a פסח. Pesach. It only follows the rules of
a פסח Pesach if it's sanctified as a פסח Pesach and brought
during this half day, from midday on the 14th until the end.
So then when it follows the rules of a פסח, Pesach, if
it is slaughtered for the sake of another sacrifice, not only do
the owners not fulfill their obligation, it's completely invalid. It has to
be burnt and so on. Okay, so הפסח בזמנו haPesach bizmano והחטאת
בכל זמן. v'haChatat bechol zman. Now a חטאת, chatat, it's always the
time for חטאת. chatat. Okay. And therefore anytime a חטאת chatat is
brought, if it is brought for some other purpose, either the animal
is completely invalid. Now by the way הפסח haPesach is a little
bit not less clear why this should be the case, but חטאת
chatat makes a lot of sense. Because the entire purpose of a
חטאת, chatat, now this is a חטאת chatat that's brought for a
sin. There are some חטאות chataot that are brought as part of
a purification process. But at least a חטאת chatat brought for a
sin is highly specific. Okay. If I went ahead and I sinned
and I ate, so there's an אשם. asham. We're going to get
to אשם. asham. I ate I ate חמץ בפסח chametz b'Pesach and
I sanctified this animal now as a חטאת. chatat. Now this is
a sin offering for Dov Linzer's חמץ בפסח. chametz b'Pesach. Okay. So
if I can't use it even for another sin I did for
eating דם dam by accident. Okay, it's specific to the sin and
to the person and so on. So therefore and it's only brought
as a result of to atone for that particular sin. So as
soon as the הלכה halacha would dictate that because it was brought
as an עולה olah with something else in mind it no longer
is being offered as my sacrifice, or if it's no longer being
offered as my sacrifice, it doesn't have any independent significance. An עולה
olah or שלמים shelamim does not have to be linked to the
owner.
Even a נזיר, nazir, does it have to be?
Okay, there are specific examples that are that are. Okay, if I
also obligated myself. But I'm just talking about it's very the nature
of the קרבן korban of an עולה olah and a שלמים shelamim
is something that is not specifically linked to an עולה. olah. You
can very easily imagine an עולה olah and a שלמים shelamim which
are just given as a נדבה nedava as a gift and have
no connection to the owner and so on. Their identity is not
wrapped up with the owner and with the circumstances of why the
owner is bringing it. So those types of things when they get
detached from the owner, even if in a particular example they are,
the owner accepted upon himself a נדר, neder, he's bringing a he's
bringing it as a נזיר, nazir, whatever the case might be, but
it can continue to live its life as generic שלמים. shelamim. Generic
ownerless שלמים shelamim is not a problematic idea. Okay, generic ownerless חטאת
chatat is a problematic idea. Ownerless חטאת chatat makes no sense. A
חטאת chatat is all about the owner's sin. And therefore once a
חטאת chatat becomes detached from the owner because it was brought for
some other purpose, it therefore becomes invalid. Now Michael says one minute,
but isn't don't we have a similar idea by an אשם? asham?
Which is actually the next line in the גמרא. Gemara. רבי אליעזר
אומר אף האשם, Rabbi Eliezer omer af ha'asham, even an אשם. asham.
Okay. הפסח בזמנו והחטאת והאשם בכל זמן, haPesach bizmano v'haChatat v'haAsham bechol
zman, just repeating what the הלכה halacha would be for him. פסח
Pesach during that period, we have to know why it's true by
פסח, Pesach, but
So
therefore an אשם Asham once it gets detached from the owner has
no longer should follow the same thing. It's about a sin, it's
about the owner. Once it gets detached it should be invalid. Okay,
so very reasonable position. Not clear what the Rabbis answer back. Okay,
but that makes a lot of sense, especially the way I explained
it. To what degree can a sacrifice have an identity that's not
connected to the owner. Okay. יוסי בן חוני אומר הנשחטים לשם פסח
ולשם חטאת פסולים. Yosi ben Choni omer ha-nishchatim leshem Pesach u'leshem Chattas
psulim. So he says he likes things to be parallel and he
says look if you shacht a פסח Pesach and a חטאת Chattas
for some other sacrifice's purpose those are invalid. So if you slaughter
some other sacrifice, an עולה olah or a שלמים, Shelamim, and you
have in mind this is going to be a חטאת, Chattas, so
the same way a חטאת Chattas brought as an עולה olah is
invalid, an עולה olah brought as a חטאת Chattas is invalid. He
wants everything to be parallel and symmetrical. Similarly if your פסח. Pesach.
Now that only works if it's on the 14th from midday on.
Okay, because that's the only time when a פסח Pesach brought as
another sacrifice is invalid. So if it's on the 14th from midday
on and you're bringing a שלמים Shelamim and you're thinking פסח Pesach
which could happen, they brought שלמים Shelamim on ערב פסח, erev Pesach,
okay, that would also be invalid.
Just want to understand something. So let's say I have two קורבנות
korbanot to make, an עולה נזיר olah Nazir and then and just
a שלמים Shelamim I obligated myself. Right. And the כהן Kohen got
up there he just thought generic. So does it at least get
me out of the obligation for שלמים Shelamim then for the other
one?
No, no, it does not. It completely does not get you out
of any obligation. It is not like you brought that sacrifice. Once
it was done שלא לשמה shelo lishma it's like a temple sacrifice.
It severs the relationship with you.
Okay. But by the way but it's
a way so you don't have to take it off from the
altar you can continue with the...
And you can eat it and whatever, exactly, you don't have to
burn it. So that's what we said when you were out... That
I can eat it?
Meaning even though it was brought...
Yeah, that's an interesting question.
I don't know if it's for me now you're saying.
I mean I don't know if it's a good question. It might
whether you as the owner have the right to eat it more
than somebody else when it's brought שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. Meaning it's
כשר kosher for you to eat. It's כשר kosher for any ישראל
Yisrael to eat if it's a שלמים Shelamim brought שלא לשמה. shelo
lishma. I would imagine certainly according to רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi that
says קדשים קלים ממון בעלים הם kodashim kalim mammon be'alim hem then
it's just your דיני ממונות dinei mamonot so you have a right
to eat it. You're eating it as your property not necessarily as
your
קרבן. korban. Do you have a particular status as פלוני'ס קרבן Ploni's
korban and so on.
Would you do the תנופה? tenufa? That's an interesting question, right? Would
you do like the waving of it after it gets to be
that time, right, of the שוק shok and whatever?
So presumably that's a really good question. Yeah. Yeah
presumably you would still retain that relationship to it to have a
right to certainly according to רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi of קדשים קלים
ממון בעלים. kodashim kalim mammon be'alim. But in general yeah presumably I'd
have to look into that but presumably you would retain that right
and you would still be seen as the owner of the קרבן
korban and the בעלים be'alim of the קרבן korban to do like
the waving if it's a שלמים Shelamim and so on. But not
enough to say that you satisfied any particular obligation. But yeah it's
an interesting question. I have to bring two שלמים. Shelamims. Yeah well
yeah like why does it... It's funny, it's still like what you're
saying is it's still my שלמים, Shelamim, I still get to wave
it, I still get to eat it, but it's not my שלמים
Shelamim I didn't fulfill my obligation. That's basically what it boils down
to. Yeah. Anyway it's a good question like would you still for
those things still be considered the owner. Okay, by the way תוספות
Tosafos, just just to clue you in on something very important because
this is going to be relevant for the whole לשמה lishma discussion.
If you look at this long תוספות, Tosafos most of it he
just discusses what's the הלכה halacha if the person has the thought
to do it specifically not for the sake of the owner. The
כהן Kohen brought Michael's שלמים Shelamim and thought it was David's. Okay
and that's going to be a discussion later in the גמרא Gemara
and תוספות Tosafos, wants to know like how do we know that
that invalidates. But anyway we'll see that later. But what I want
you to see is the last line of this big תוספות Tosafos
where he says right above the word הפסח ha-Pesach where he says
like
this: ובפרק המפקיד uve'perek ha-mafkid right above that word הפסח ha-Pesach the
new תוספות Tosafos פירשתי הא דמחשבה פוסלת בקדשים perashti ha de'machshava poseles
be'kodashim when we say when the כהנים kohanim have the wrong thought
it invalidates אי בדיבור הזבח נעשה שלא לשמה או אפילו במחשבה. i
be'dibur ha-zevach na'ase shelo lishma o afilu be'machshava. Do you have to
articulate the thought or is it even just what's going through their
head? Okay and that's really an important question and there's a whole
debate of רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafos and it's in all the various
whole range of areas where there's a question about somebody שלא לשמה,
shelo lishma, does the thought have to be articulated or not? So
that's just important to be aware of at the outset that that's
not clear in the גמרא Gemara and that gets an important discussion.
Okay so back to the משנה. Mishna. שמעון
אחי עזריה אומר, Shimon achi Azarya omer, Shimon the brother of Azarya
says. The reason he's called... the brother of עזריה Azaryah's because עזריה
Azaryah basically supported him in his learning. They did a whole, you
know, a whole what's it called, יששכר זבולון Yissachar Zevulun arrangement. Okay,
so שמעון אחי עזריה אומר: Shimon achi Azaryah omer: שחטן לשם גבוה
מהן כשרים, לשם נמוך מהן פסולים. Shachtan l'shem gavo'ah mehen kesherim, l'shem
namuch mehen pesulim. If you slaughter it for the sake of something
higher level, you slaughter a שלמים Shlamim as an עולה, Olah, then
it's kosher. If you slaughter it as something at a lower level,
an עולה Olah as a שלמים, Shlamim, it's invalid. So now, invalid,
the question is like this: invalid really means, you know, because here
the whole word is כשרים kesherim means it's kosher qua קרבן, korban,
even if you didn't fulfill your obligation. So פסולים pesulim here means
the whole קרבן korban's invalid, not only the owner didn't fulfill their
obligation. So an עולה Olah that was slaughtered as a שלמים, Shlamim,
you'd have to bring it out and burn it, you know, or
whatever, חטאת Chatas brought it, well, for, you know, anything you basically
have to burn it, you can't offer it on the altar. If
you bring it for something lower on the thing, you've like,
you know, impinged, you know, offended its קדושה, kedushah, you intended something
lower on the scale, it's completely invalid. If you do it higher
on the scale, it's kosher and the question in the גמרא Gemara
is, maybe he's going to be when he's, maybe when he's lenient,
he's even more lenient than the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Maybe he
says if you do a שלמים Shlamim as an עולה, Olah, maybe
it's not just kosher that you can bring it, maybe even the
owner's fulfilled their obligation. Okay, that's not clear. But his first big
חידוש chiddush is if you do it lower on the scale, it's
completely
invalid. And if you do it higher on the scale, then it
remains כשר kasher and maybe it even, you fulfill your obligation.
שחטן לשם גבוה מהן כשרים, לשם נמוך מהן פסולים. כיצד? קדשי קדשים
ששחטן לשם קדשים קלים,
Shachtan l'shem gavo'ah mehen kesherim, l'shem namuch mehen
pesulim. Keitzad? Kodshei kodashim sheshachtan l'shem kodshim kalim, something that is the
most holy like an עולה Olah that's brought for something that's a
קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, פסולים pesulim is invalid, like a שלמים. Shlamim.
פסולים לשם, קדשים קלים ששחטן לשם קדשי קדשים, כשרים. Pesulim, l'shem, kodshim
kalim sheshachtan l'shem kodshei kodashim, kesherim. If you bring something like a
שלמים Shlamim and you bring it as an עולה Olah or a
חטאת, Chatas, it's kosher. Now, of course, even within קדשים קלים kodshim
kalim and קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, there's a hierarchy. You know, an
עולה Olah is seen to be higher than a חטאת Chatas and
so on and he gets to that. הבכור והמעשר ששחטן לשם שלמים,
Habechor vehamaser sheshachtan l'shem Shlamim, בכור ומעשר, bechor umaaser, which are pretty
close to being a שלמים, Shlamim, okay, but they here are considered
to be lower. Why? Because you don't put the blood on four
corners of the altar, you don't put your hand to rest on
the head of it, you don't bring the flour and the wine
with it, you don't wave the thigh and the breast. Okay, so
these are even though so because of the way their fewer demands
in terms of the עבודה, avodah, that's seen as a signal that
these are of a lower level of קדושה, kedushah, even though they
are effectively types of שלמים. Shlamim. Okay, so even so, that is
even a hierarchy that matters here. Okay, so שחטן לשם גבוה מהן
כשרים. Shachtan l'shem gavo'ah mehen kesherim. So if you did it up,
went up on the level of the שלמים, Shlamim, it's
kosher. לשלמים ששחטן לשם בכור או לשם מעשר, פסולים L'Shlamim sheshachtan l'shem
bechor o l'shem maaser, pesulim are invalid and presumably completely invalid, you
have to burn it off of the altar, it's completely פסול. pasul.
You had a question, Michael?
Yeah, I mean this is talking about the use of לשמן, l'shman,
which we're taking to mean the initial to שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah,
which I guess is the same synonym. But I mean this is
taking no position as let's say there was initial to לשמה, lishmah,
but then, you know, the זריקה. zerikah.
So that's what I said when you were out, that this applies
to all of the four עבודות, avodos, which is going to be
a משנה mishna coming up. We're starting by focusing on the שחיטה.
shchitah. Interestingly, the שחיטה shchitah doesn't have to even be done by
a כהן, kohen, but it's really about any one of the four
key עבודות: avodos: the שחיטה, shchitah, קבלה kabbalah catching the blood, הולכה
holachah bringing it to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, and זריקה zerikah throwing it
on the altar. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
למה לי למתני אלא? Lama li l'misnei ela? Why does it say
אלא? ela? You know, if you slaughter them שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah,
they're kosher, except, but they didn't, weren't עלו לבעלים לשם חובה. olah
l'ba'alim l'shem chovah. You'd say and they weren't עלו לבעלים לשם חובה.
olah l'ba'alim l'shem chovah. Something I'm always trying to figure out in
my writing, do I add the word however or but or do
I just juxtapose the sentences? Okay, anyway, okay, so why do you
have to say אלא? ela? עלו לבעלים לשם חובה. Olah l'ba'alim l'shem
chovah. ליתני ולא עלו לבעלים לשם חובה. Lisni v'lo olah l'ba'alim l'shem
chovah. הא קמשמע לן, Ha kamashma lan, this teaches you, לבעלים הוא
דלא עלו לשם חובה, l'ba'alim hu d'lo olu l'shem chovah, אבל בקדושתייהו
קיימי. aval bekadushataihu kaimi. The
only problem is the owner didn't fulfill their obligation. But in all
other ways, they are a completely have their קדושה, kedushah, don't think
that in any way their קדושה kedushah has been compromised. Okay, so
what would be, how might I have thought their קדושה kedushah's compromised?
I mean, you're already telling me it's kosher. To tell me the
following: ואסור לשנויי בהו. va'assur l'shinuyei behu. Don't go ahead and think
that, you know, I can once I had one wrong thought, I
can have another wrong thought since, you know, it's not going to
affect it, it's already not being עלו לבעלים. olah l'ba'alim.
Okay, ואסור לשנויי בהו. va'assur l'shinuyei behu. כדרבא דאמר רבא, Kid'Rava d'amar
Rava, עולה ששחטן שלא לשמה, olah sheshachtan shelo lishmah, just because you
slaughtered it שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah, אסור לזרוק דמה שלא לשמה. asur
lizrok damah shelo lishmah. Don't go ahead and say, well, might as
well just throw the blood for the sake of a שלמים Shlamim
also since that was the thought I had when I slaughtered it.
No. All of the demands that it has, which is interesting, right?
It's because these demands are not just in order to make sure
it's kosher, have the right thing in mind. It's קדושה kedushah as
a קרבן. korban. somehow makes demands that you treat it as an
עולה olah should be treated. And the way an עולה, olah, to
use that as an example, should be treated is, not only you
throw the blood here and you slaughter the animal there and you
do this with the limbs, the way it's treated is that when
you're doing the עבודות, avodot, you're doing it with the mindset of
what type of a קרבן korban it is. So since this still
has the full קדושה kedusha and status of an עולה, olah, it
still demands that every עבודה avoda be done properly, even though admittedly,
if you did it improperly it would not invalidate. You know, but
look, if you throw the blood on one corner and not on
two corners, you also didn't invalidate. It's also כשר, kosher, okay? And
nevertheless, you're not supposed to you're supposed to do it the right
way. Okay. So, איבעיא להו. ibaia lehu. Now the גמרא Gemara asks
a question. איבעית אימא, iba'it eima, if you want I could say
סברא, sevara, איבעית אימא iba'it eima קרא. kra. I can I can
either sort of show this to you from just logic or from
a verse. This idea that you still have to treat it the
right way. איבעית אימא iba'it eima
סברא, sevara, משום דשיני בה כל הני לשני בה ולאזיל? mishum deshani
bei kol hani lishni bei velazeil? Just because you made one thing
wrong, you should make other things wrong? You know, which is like
really, like what justifies continuing to do things wrong? Some there's another
place that the גמרא Gemara has this phrase of like, if you
just ate one clove of garlic, you know, and your breath smells
bad, doesn't mean you should keep on eating garlic. Okay, it means
you should go brush your teeth. Okay, ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, if
you want,
קרא. kra. I'll learn it from a
פסוק. pasuk. מוצא שפתיך תשמור ועשית כאשר נדרת לה' אלוהיך נדבה כאשר
דברת בפיך.
motza sefatecha tishmor ve-asita ka'asher nadarta lashem elokecha
nedava ka'asher dibarta beficha. As you as you vow to God a
gift, as you spoke with your words. Now נדר, neder, one thing
you have to know is, in the תורה, Torah, the difference of
נדר neder and נדבה nedava are relatively interchangeable. But in חז"ל, Chazal,
they mean very different things and חז"ל Chazal read this in the
פסוקים pesukim as well, that the word נדר neder means a vow
that I accept a personal obligation. הרי עלי. harei alai. You accept
upon yourself, okay, to do you know, to do something. A נדבה,
nedava, like if you think about וידור ישראל נדר לאמר אם אלוהים
עמדי—no, vayidor Yisrael neder lemor im elokim imadi that's יעקב. Yaakov. That's
another נדר. neder. ויידור ישראל נדר ויאמר אם נתון תיתן את העם
הזה בידי והחרמתי את עריהם.
vayidor Yisrael neder
vayomar
im naton titein et ha'am hazeh beyadi vehacharamti et areihem. But יעקב
Yaakov is also נודר נדר. noder neder. What does it say by
יעקב? Yaakov? It says וידר יעקב נדר. vayidar Yaakov neder. אם יהיה
אלוהים עמדי ושמרני. im yihyeh elokim imadi ushmarani. If God does this,
so a נדר neder is a personal obligation in the תורה, Torah,
and חז"ל Chazal understand it by קרבנות korbanot to be—it's actually funny,
that's not what it means when we deal with נדרים, nedarim, but
anyway חז"ל Chazal understand by קרבנות korbanot it means I accept upon
myself a personal obligation to bring a קרבן, korban, עולה olah or
שלמים. shelamim. נדבה nedava is a gift, and therefore it means that
כל נדיב לבו יביאה, kol nediv libo yevi'eha, etc. And therefore what
that means is I sanctify this animal as an עולה olah or
שלמים shelamim but I don't accept it as a personal obligation to
do. I just sanctify the animal. So here it says, if you
the same way you made a נדר, neder, you know, just as
you made your vow, it should be a נדבה. nedava. So the
גמרא Gemara says היי נדבה? hai nedava? What do you mean it
should be a נדבה? nedava? נדר הוא. neder hu. It's a נדר.
neder. It should be כאשר נדרת לה' אלוהיך נדר. ka'asher nadarta lashem
elokecha neder. What does it mean נדבה? nedava? Okay, so the so
the you don't
need to say that, כאשר נדרת. ka'asher nadarta.
Oh, right. אלא אם—this ela im is how to read it. אם
כמה שנדרת עשית, im kema shenadarta asita, if כאשר נדרת, ka'asher nadarta,
then it's
then
you know, then it's then, ייהא נדר, yehei neder, then it works
as a נדר, neder, okay, and it'll you'll fulfill your obligation. נדר
neder is your personal obligation. So if כאשר נדרת, ka'asher nadarta, then
if you did it כאשר נדרת ka'asher nadarta it works as a
נדר. neder. ואי לאו, ve-i lav, but if you don't do it
כאשר נדרת, ka'asher nadarta, if you had a different thing in mind,
נדבה יהא. nedava yehei. It'll be a נדבה. nedava. So that's a
good basis to say the idea that, you know, שלא עלו לבעלים—this
shelo alu liva'alim principle of the משנה. Mishna. The גמרא Gemara doesn't
quote it for this purpose. The גמרא Gemara quotes it to teach
you that you don't keep on making, you know, you don't have
a license to keep on making changes. But it also serves as
a nice basis for our משנה. Mishna. How do you know that
if you made a change, it still is a כשר kosher קרבן
korban but it's not עולה? olah? כאשר נדרת, ka'asher nadarta, if you
do it כאשר נדרת, ka'asher nadarta, then it's לה' אלוהיך. lashem elokecha.
But if it's not כאשר נדרת, ka'asher nadarta, then it's נדבה. nedava.
Then it still works as a נדבה, nedava, as an animal that
you sanctified but you don't fulfill a personal obligation, okay? ובנדבה מי
שרי לשנויי בה? uvinedava mi shari leshunoyei bah? And if it's a
נדבה, nedava, okay, you don't have a right to change a נדבה.
nedava. If I sanctified an animal as an עולה, olah, I have
to do it the right way. Okay, so its status as a
קרבן, korban, it is full level of its sanctity. The sanctity of
it as a קרבן korban has not been compromised. It's just like
a נדבה. nedava. It no longer functions to satisfy your נדר. neder.
It no longer functions for you to satisfy your obligation, okay? All
right. So רש"י Rashi just by the way parses the פסוק. pasuk.
אם מוצא שפתיך תשמור ועשית, im motza sefatecha tishmor ve'asita, then if
you did it like you said, then נדר. neder. אשר—אז יהא נדר
אשר נדרת. az yehei neder asher nadarta. ואי לאו נדבה. ve-i lav
nedava. Okay. So if it's—so if you do everything right, then כאשר
נדרת לה' אלוהיך, ka'asher nadarta lashem elokecha, then it's a נדר. neder.
If you didn't do everything right, it still is a נדבה. nedava.
So that's a nice basis, which is not, again, the גמרא Gemara
didn't
quote. Okay, but
but
but but but the don't think that the קדושה kedushah has been
compromised, the קדושה kedushah has not been compromised in any way and
you still have to do everything, you know, לכתחילה lechatchila the way
it should be done. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay.
אמר ליה רבינא לרב פפא. Amar leih Ravina l'Rav Pappa. רבינא Ravina
said to רב פפא. Rav Pappa. לא הוית
גבן באורתא בתחומא בי חרמך.
Lo haveit gaban
b'orta b'tchuma bei Charmach.
You weren't with us last night on Friday night in the תחום,
tchum, in the תחום tchum of שבת. Shabbos. So our בית מדרש
Beis Medrash you were outside, you were away for שבת Shabbos and
you couldn't come, you know, come to the בית מדרש Beis Medrash
even if you would have been willing to walk, you were outside
the תחום. tchum. It's too bad you weren't with our בית מדרש
Beis Medrash in our בית מדרש Beis Medrash last night on Friday
night, okay, בי חרמך. bei Charmach. דרמי רבא מילי מעלייתא אהדדי D'rami
Rava mili me'alyata ahadadei because רבא Rava showed, you know, made a
really good point. He showed what looked like a contradiction between two
different statements. ושני להו, V'shani lehu, and he gave an excellent
answer. מאי מילי מעלייתא? Mai mili me'alyata? What was this really good
teaching of רבא? Rava? תנן, Tnan, our משנה Mishnah teaches, כל הזבחים
שנזבחו שלא לשמן. Kol hazvachim shenizbechu shelo lishman. If done שלא לשמן,
shelo lishman, it's כשר kasher but the בעלים be'alim didn't fulfill their
obligation. טעמא דשלא לשמן, Ta'ama d'shelo lishman, now the reason is and
he's very careful about how you articulate things is it כל הזבחים.
kol hazvachim. What is the difference between saying כל הזבחים שלא נזבחו
לשמן kol hazvachim shelo nizbechu lishman or שנזבחו שלא לשמן? shenizbechu shelo
lishman? All sacrifice
that were not slaughtered for their right purpose, that's one way of
saying it, that were not slaughtered for their right purpose or the
way our משנה Mishnah says it is that was slaughtered for their
not right purpose. Okay. The difference is if it was neither for
the right purpose nor for the wrong purpose. Okay. To say not
slaughtered for the right means anything that was not the right thing
in mind is going to be invalid. Slaughtered for the not right
purpose means only if you have the wrong thing in mind but
if you have a blank, you don't have intention an intention one
way or the other, it's going to be כשר. kasher. It's the
middle case. Okay. So, תנן, Tnan, our משנה Mishnah says, כל הזבחים
שנזבחו שלא לשמן. Kol hazvachim shenizbechu shelo lishman. They were slaughtered for
the wrong reason. טעמא דשלא לשמן, Ta'ama d'shelo lishman, the reason it's
invalid is it was slaughtered for the wrong reason. הא
סתמא, Ha stama, if it was just slaughtered without thinking, you know,
the כהנים Kohanim are very busy. It's like whatever, just give me
the sacrifice, שח שח שח שח שח. shach shach shach shach shach.
Okay. They're not going to try to be keeping in mind, you
know, whose whose is this, what type of sacrifice. There's a little
they have to pay attention because they have to know where to
slaughter and where to throw the blood but whatever. Anyway, they just
were blank mind for most of the time. Okay. הא סתמא, Ha
stama, what you really need for heavy operations is you need one
guy there who's the dispatcher. You know, these are the כהנים Kohanim
are situated over there and they're getting the עולות. olos. This guy,
this group of כהנים Kohanim are situated here, they're getting the שלמים.
shlamim. This group is situated they're getting חטאת chatas and you have
one guy that's just dispatching the sacrifices. Anyway, I don't know if
they did it that way but that would make a lot of
sense. Anyway, whatever. So but you as the כהן, Kohen, the smartest
thing for you to do is keep a blank mind cause you
can only make things worse. Okay. So anyway הא סתמא, Ha stama,
well if you say סתמא stama works. הא סתמא, Ha stama, the
implication of our משנה Mishnah is if you don't have a particular
intent, עלו נמי לבעלים לשם חובה. alu nami l'be'alim l'shem chovah. It
also is good. The only problem is a bad intent. אלמא סתמי
נמי כלשמן דמי. Alma stamei nami k'lishman dami. You see if you
have a blank intent it's like you had the right intent.
What about this distinction between the necessity for an oral declaration?
No, that would mean that if you say סתמא שלא לשמן stama
shelo lishman it means that the only time it's bad is if
you verbally say the wrong
thing. No, I did not say that you needed verbally to say
the right thing. I said when you said that the bad מחשבה
machshavah invalidates, okay. You now if you say סתם stam doesn't work,
then you might verbally have to say the right thing. But if
you say סתם stam works, what it means is you don't have
to say anything, okay, but it and it only becomes bad if
you think the wrong thing and thinking the wrong thing might actually
mean saying the wrong thing. Okay. So this way is saying basically
it's all fine until you think and or say the wrong thing.
Okay. ורמינהי, Ur'minhi, but I'll ask you on this. כל גט שנכתב
שלא לשם אשה פסול. Kol get shenichtav shelo l'shem ishah pasul. Any
גט get written not for this woman is invalid. וסתמא נמי פסול.
V'stama nami pasul. Now the language as the גמרא Gemara is going
to say is the same. It didn't say that was not written
for this woman. It said that's written for not this woman, written
for a different woman it's invalid. But nevertheless we know that the
הלכה halachah is, how we know the הלכה halachah is, we'll find
out in a minute, that if you didn't explicitly intend this woman
it's invalid. So just trust us on this for now. Okay. So
a קרבן korban with a blank intent סתם stam works, for a
גט get it has to be explicitly for this
woman. ושני, V'shani, okay, that's always an answer, but let's take a
look. Okay. ושני, V'shani, so that's the question. What is a when
you need something to be לשמה? lishmah? What is it when you
need something to be לשמה? lishma? What is the story when you
don't have a wrong thought or you don't have a right thought?
You have no thought. ושני V'shani and his answer was זבחים בסתם
לשמה zvachim b'stam lishma ועומדים אשה בסתם לאו לגירושין עומדת. v'omdim isha
b'stama lav l'geirushin omedet. Okay, a sacrifice is you know the סתם
stam case, the unexplicated case means that they are עומדים, omdim, they
are like, they are like you know designated for
for the right purpose whereas a woman is not automatically designated to
be divorced. So what this means is the following, I mean one
way to explain this, a simple way to explain this is, an
animal is sanctified. This sheep here is sanctified as an עולה. olah.
So therefore almost by definition any act that I do to this
sheep, I mean if I'm doing the right thing I'm supposed to
do with an עולה, olah, is considered to be for the sake
of an עולה. olah. Its קדושה kedusha defines the nature of the
act. We're not talking about what thought I have to have in
my head. The purpose I have to think that it's לשם עולה
l'shem olah is so that the act of slaughtering is defined as
an עולה olah slaughtering. The act of throwing the blood is defined
as an עולה. olah. It doesn't matter what's in my head. What's
in my head matters to define the nature of the act. So
since the thing I'm dealing with is an עולה, olah, as long
as I don't think the wrong thing, those acts are properly
defined, סתם לשמן עומדים. stam lishmon omdim. By the way, an interesting
test of does it work, does it mean that it's what I'm
thinking or does it mean it's automatically defined is let's say you
have because you could say well you're in the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, you know it's an עולה, olah, that somehow shapes what's subconsciously,
but let's say for example you deal- תוספות Tosafot has a question
about let's say you're dealing with a minor, okay? So like minors
we tend to assume that they're not having like you know they
don't have any thoughts, I mean they do have thoughts whatever, no
halachically meaningful ones or whatever. So maybe it doesn't matter. The point
here is not that because it's an עולה olah that makes me
think the right thing or somehow it defines my thoughts in a
particular way. The best way to understand this is the whole reason
I have to have לשמה lishma is that the acts should be
defined in a particular way. And if this animal is sanctified as
an עולה olah any act that's done by it is defined as
an עולה olah act, as a proper act, unless there's something that
actively redefines it. Okay, so that's why an עולה olah is סתם
לשמה עומדי. stam lishma omei. Now an אשה isha is not סתם
לגט stam l'get because I have to go ahead and write a
גט get for a woman. There is nothing objectively that says that
if I'm writing a גט get with a person's name. Now again
if it has the person's social security number or whatever you know
then you could say that's automatically being defined for that person. But
remember you know you're just writing שרה בת רחל. Sarah Bas Rachel.
Okay, there could be a million שרה בת רחל Sarah Bas Rachel
and even if she's married to a יוסף בן שמעון, Yosef Ben
Shimon, there could be other שרה בת רחל Sarah Bas Rachel married
to a יוסף בן שמעון. Yosef Ben Shimon. There's nothing that defines
this גט get to be for that particular woman. Okay, and רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafot basically or you know go out and say
even let's say
that
this woman basically just now committed adultery against her husband and the
husband you know and the husband has to divorce her and has
made public declarations that he's going to divorce her whatever the case
is, even so meaning I'm sort of saying the גט get is
not לסתם listam for you know to be מגרש migareish this
woman, okay. The גמרא's Gemara frame here is what's
גמרא's Gemara frame, אשה לאו סתמא לאו לגירושין עומדת. isha is lav
stama lav l'geirushin omedet. Tos says okay what if there's a case
that you know the woman is in the process of getting divorced,
she's separating from her husband the whole thing etc. תוספות Tosafot says
nevertheless there's still nothing that means that this גט get has to
be for this woman even if it's in a context where you
know the husband's looking to divorce his wife they're in the process
he's going to write it. Okay, if there it just the fact
of her name being in it right doesn't like define it as
being for her because you're not starting with like by the קדשים,
kodshim, right because first of all you could write another גט get
for her. So there's nothing unless you specifically make it her גט
get and have her in mind. Okay, if it was just automatically
written with nothing in mind, blank mind, you know, I'm just the
סופר, sofer, you just tell me names. That's a good way of
thinking about it because it's hard to get over the point like
if I know the woman's about to get divorced whatever then I
am having her in mind. But imagine this, okay, I'm just you
know I'm just reading names off of a screen you know about
trying to write the גט get or whatever. I'm just reading whatever
names I'm seeing are being written, I'm just copying those names. So
even though the reality is that there's a woman with this name
who's ready to get divorced that doesn't make it that this is
for that woman. What defines this act as being for the woman?
As opposed to a קרבן, korban, since it's an act done to
an
עולה, olah, it's the שחיטה shechting of an עולה, olah, it's the
throwing of the blood of an עולה. olah. This is not the
writing of a גט get for that woman unless you have in
mind that woman. Makes a lot of sense. Okay.
But when we say that woman though we don't mean you have
to like picture her in your mind and like oh yeah that's
like you know the woman who
lives on whatever, you just having in mind the woman named שרה
בת רחל Sarah Bas Rachel and you're well that's an interesting question
because like there are multiple women named שרה בת רחל. Sarah Bas
Rachel. How does it mean like you know?
What does it mean?
Well it could mean you know if I'm a שליח shliach and
I'm telling you then I'm sort of saying or if I'm the
husband I'm saying you for my wife whose name is. But there
has to be something that concretizes it, you know? Okay, anyway. So
it says like that. So, so that's a very nice distinction. Alright.
Now, it raises interesting questions of when you deal with something that
is a physical object that could define the act, but it doesn't
have קדושה kedusha the same way a קרבן korban does that you
sort of that the קרבן korban has a real status there that
define could define everything done to it. So for example, let's say
you're supposed to I don't know make a knot K-N-O-T ציצית לשמה.
tzitzit lishma. Okay, and you're knotting your ציצית tzitzit and you're just
you know you've done it a million times you know you're not
even paying attention you're just doing it automatically. Your hands are doing
it no muscle memory. So do you say look, the reality of
making ציצית tzitzit on a בגד beged is לשם ציצית, leshem tzitzit,
you know? So at least there you're starting with an object and
the thing is done to the object what needs to be done
to the object, okay? There's no reason this paper that I'm writing
a גט get has to be done for this woman, you know
whatever. There's nothing that defines it but ציצית tzitzit that are done
properly it's considered to be an act of טיית ציצית. tiyat tzitzit.
So תוספות Tosafot talks about ברית מילה brit milah the same way
that a ברית מילה שלא לשמה brit milah shelo lishma is invalid
but תוספות Tosafot says but if you do a ברית מילה brit
milah with a blank mind or even a non-Jew according to one
opinion in the גמרא Gemara is kosher to do a ברית מילה,
brit milah, it's kosher because סתם ברית מילה לשמה עומד. stam brit
milah lishma omed. Okay, an act of removing the foreskin is defined
as done for the purpose of ברית מילה, brit milah, okay, it
is defined as an act of ברית מילה brit milah until you
redefine it as something else. Alright. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Where were we?
One minute.
Okay, fine. Moving back to the גמרא. Gemara. So there's a very
important discussion in general סתם ולשמה עומד stam u'lishma omed which is
very easy to say by קדשים kodashim which are sanctified and have
that whole identity to the object that you are working on it's
already defined with the sanctity of an עולה. olah. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara just wants to know what led you rather than
what we just did which is exploring the why of the difference
it wants to know how you know that this is the these
halachas are what you said they were that led us to our
problem. So let's take a look. Okay, so וזבחים בסתם כשרין מנלן
v'zvachim b'stam k'shirin minalan and how do you know that a זבחים
zvachim done for סתם stam is kosher? אילימא מהא דתנן ilima me-ha
d'tnan כל הזבחים שנזבחו שלא לשמן kol hazvachim shenizbechu shelo lishmam
they were slaughtered for their wrong purpose ולא תני שלא נזבחו לשמן
v'lo tani shelo nizbechu lishmam you didn't say that were not slaughtered
for their right purpose. So it means that only if it was
wrong is it invalid. גבי גט נמי gabi get nami by גט
get also הכא תני hacha tani כל גט שנכתב שלא לשם אשה
kol get shenichtav shelo l'shem isha פסול pasul any גט get that
was written for not for this woman is invalid for meaning for
a different woman. ולא תני שלא נכתב לשם אשה v'lo tani shelo
nechtav l'shem isha it didn't say that was not written for this
woman. It was said that was written for not this woman it
was written for a different woman. So it sounds אלא מהא ela
me-ha so you can't prove it from the language of that משנה
mishna it's the exact same phraseology as what we have by us.
אלא מהא דתנן ela me-ha d'tnan כיצד לשמן ושלא לשמן. keitzad lishman
v'shelo lishman. So here here's how we're going to prove first we're
going to prove what it means by קדשים kodashim and then we're
going to prove that it means that it means something else. So
the first thing to prove is that by קדשים kodashim neutral is
okay.
It
says what's considered לשמן ושלא לשמן lishman v'shelo lishman it says a
later משנה mishna talks about let's say you had two intents at
the beginning of a process or process a you thought about לשמו
lishmo and at the end of the process or process b you
thought about שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. Does it remain kosher does it
become פסול pasul etc. Okay so it says כיצד לשמן ושלא לשמן
keitzad lishman v'shelo lishman what's considered to be for the right reason
not the right reason? לשם פסח ולשם שלמים. leshem pesach u-leshem shelamim.
So you started the slaughtering was לשם פסח leshem pesach and the
catching of the blood was לשם שלמים. leshem shelamim. So טעמא דאמר
לשם פסח ולשם שלמים tama d'amar leshem pesach u-leshem shelamim so you
see the example of שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is to actually be
giving it an actively different identity שלמים shelamim rather than פסח. pesach.
והא לשם פסח וסתם v'ha leshem pesach u-stam but if you just
didn't have the thought of a פסח pesach when you caught the
blood so כשר kasher it would be kosher. So you see the
example the משנה mishna gives of שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is a
wrong name not the absence of the right name. אלמא סתמא כלישמן
דמי alma stama k'lishman dami you see that סתם stam works. מהא
אמר לא דילמא שאני התם דאמר כל העושה על דעת ראשונה הוא
עושה. me-ha amar lo dilma shani hatam d'amar kol ha-oseh al da'at
rishonah hu oseh.
Since you started by doing it לשם פסח leshem pesach therefore if
you had a if you didn't say anything for the other things
it would be defined by the original thought. So that's why you
had to give an example of actively giving it a different name
שלמים. shelamim. But that doesn't mean that if you did from the
outset blank that it would work it only if you start the
right way and then you do it blank it works. אלא מסיפא
ela mi-seifa fine let's go from the end of that משנה. mishna.
שלא לשמן ולשמן shelo lishman v'lishman the first עבודה avodah was the
wrong thing and the second one was the right thing. What does
it mean? לשם שלמים ולשם פסח. leshem shelamim u-leshem pesach. The שחיטה
shchita was for שלמים shelamim and the catching of the blood was
for פסח. pesach. So that's invalid whatever or maybe it is it's
valid doesn't matter. But anyway טעמא דאמר לשם שלמים ולשם פסח. tama
d'amar leshem shelamim u-leshem pesach. So the reason that is a problem
is because the שלא לשמו shelo lishmo was the actively a different
name it was a שלמים. shelamim. That's why it's invalid. הא סתמא
ha stama if it was blank for the שחיטה... shchita... and פסח
Pesach for the catching of the blood, ושם פסח כשר ushem Pesach
kasher would be כשר. kasher. The only thing that makes it לא
לשמה lo lishmo is you actively gave it a name of a
שלמים. shelamim. And he says no, maybe if you said nothing the
whole thing it would be invalid. The reason blank plus פסח Pesach
works is because the פסח Pesach at the end redefines the
beginning. יוכיח סוף על תחילתו yochiach sof al techilato that let the
end thought of the the פסח Pesach for catching the blood define
that the blank for שחיטה shechita was פסח. Pesach. אינמי, Inami, אי
דקתני לשמה ושלא לשמה אמרת לשמה ושלא לשמה, ei dekatani lishmo veshelo
lishmo amrat lishmo veshelo lishmo, or we gave the you know the
the parallel of what we gave at the beginning. So the fact
that we used the example there that what שלא לשמה shelo lishmo
was we said for שלמים shelamim and an active different name and
not a blank was not to say that blank generally works. It's
to say that if you have the right thing and a blank
it works. If you have פסח Pesach at the beginning and then
a blank or a blank and then פסח Pesach it works. It
doesn't prove that blank in general works. Okay so you can't prove
anything from that. אלא מהא, Ella me-ha, from the following משנה. mishna.
לשם שישה דברים הזבח נזבח. Leshem shisha devarim hazevach nizbach. For the
six things a sacrifice is slaughtered. לשם זבח, Leshem zevach, okay it's
slaughtered. Now the question here does this mean that you have to
be thinking about this? Does this mean again well that's part of
our question okay but like you know anyway we normally it's rare
that we would say that if you weren't thinking these things you
invalidate the sacrifice but anyway it would be weird to say that.
Anyway לשם זבח Leshem zevach it has to be for the sake
of the קרבן korban that's presumably the normal לשמה lishmo that we're
talking about. לשם זובח, Leshem zoveach, the owner. So those are the
two we normally focus on, the קרבן korban and the owner. Here
four others. לשם שם, Leshem Shem, you have to be thinking this
is for God, it's a good thing to think about. לשם אשים,
Leshem ishim, this is to be burnt, that the right things that
are going to be burnt on the מזבח mizbeach would be brought
on the מזבח. mizbeach. לשם ריח, Leshem reiach, that the smoke of
it should go up which means basically don't roast it off the
מזבח mizbeach and then put it on the מזבח mizbeach then you
don't have the nice fragrant smoke going up when you burn it.
לשם ניחוח, Leshem nichoach, and that it should be for a...
these go together right, ריח ניחוח?
reiach nichoach? Yeah but it's described yeah right. Why are we seeing
these two? I don't know, that's the way the גמרא Gemara understands
it that they're separate ideas. Okay, ומהו לשם ניחוח? umahu leshem nichoach?
רש"י Rashi says
לשם ניחוח leshem nichoach doesn't mean that the smell has to be
good it means that it has to be done to for you
know for נחת רוח nachas ruach for God, to do it in
order to satisfy what God has commanded us. Okay, וחטאת ואשם לשם
חטא, Ve-chatas ve-asham leshem chet, and חטאת chatas and אשם asham for
the sake of the sin. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yose, so
anyway we're not going to try to unpack that, that's fascinating. What
do these other things in addition to owner and sacrifice mean? And
if you're not thinking these things or whatever you're invalidating it? That's
a fascinating משנה mishna we'll get to it. That's not our point.
Our point now is the רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose point. אמר רבי
יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yose, אף מי שלא היה בלבו לשם אחת מכל
אלו, af mi shelo haya belibo leshem achas mikol elu, even if
you weren't thinking any of these things, כשר, kasher, it's כשר. kasher.
Why? שתנאי בית דין הוא, she-tenai Beis Din hu, that it's a
condition that בית דין Beis Din stipulated. Now what does that mean
בית דין Beis Din stipulated?
So
the גמרא Gemara is going to read it the following way. I'll
tell you a different way you could have read it in a
minute. But the גמרא Gemara is going to read it, בית דין
Beis Din actually is making a rule... no that's what you would
have thought and then it wouldn't have been a proof, so that's
not the way the גמרא Gemara is reading it. The way the
גמרא Gemara is reading it is that בית דין Beis Din puts
down a rule and asks, says כהנים, Kohanim, the rule is do
not be thinking about anything when you are slaughtering the... when you
are doing your עבודה. avoda. Why? Because if you start thinking about
things you'll think about the wrong things. If you say oh this
is an עולה ola so you'll sometimes say an עולה ola when
it's a חטאת chatas so better not to think about anything. So
rather than... so that's how they're reading the תנאי בית דין. tenai
Beis Din. בית דין Beis Din is making... which is a funny
word of תנאי, tenai, you should have said תקנת בית דין הוא
takanas Beis Din hu or whatever. And now the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, so the
גמרא Gemara says, אזקינו בית דין דלא לימא לשמה דילמא אתי למימר
שלא לשמה, Askinu Beis Din delo leima lishmo dilma asi leimei shelo
lishmo, so בית דין Beis Din stipulates don't say, don't try to
say, notice by the way the word למימר leimei say, which gets
to the question of say.
Or you'd say to yourself.
I understand, I do understand. Anyway don't say slash think the right
thing, don't think anything, because if you're thinking trying to think the
right thing there'll be times where you'll think or say the wrong
thing. So now the גמרא Gemara says ואי סלקא דעתך סתמא פסול,
ve-i salka dachas tama pasul, okay so it's very nice בית דין
Beis Din told the כהנים Kohanim not to think, but if it's
invalid if you're not
thinking, קיימי בית דין ומתנו מידי דאתי לידי פסול, kaymi Beis Din
umasnu midi de-asi lidei pasul, how could they say this? Now all
the קרבנות korbanos should be פסול. pasul. So since בית דין Beis
Din are telling us not to think, obviously if without thinking it's
כשר. kasher. Now that's all very nice if that's how you read
תנאי בית דין. tenai Beis Din. But I totally agree with Michael
that the normal way of reading תנאי בית דין tenai Beis Din
is that בית דין Beis Din is sort of like defining what
your intent is. It's sort of like you're saying you know any
any food left in this fridge by ערב פסח Erev Pesach is
defined to have been made הפקר. hefker. You know any you know
any object left unattended in this room by the end of the
week is hereby defined that you are making it הפקר. hefker. I
am I am making a statement, you're in my space, playing by
my rules, you're implicitly agreeing to the conditions that I frame and
you you have now made your object הפקר hefker because you were
in my בית מדרש Beis Medrash and you left your object there
by the end of the week and there was a big sign
up that you definitely saw that said that if you leave it
at the end of the week you're making it הפקר. hefker. Okay?
So that's what you would think בית דין Beis Din is. בית
דין *Beis Din* is getting up and saying any כהן *kohein* that
slaughters any animal or that does any עבודה *avodah*, we are hereby
by default defining that your intention is, I mean unless you actively
say the opposite, okay, that your intention is the right intention for
that קרבן korban, *korban*. Okay. So maybe therefore the only reason it
works is because they went ahead and they made that תנאי *tnai*.
It doesn't mean that without that תנאי *tnai* it automatically would have
been defined as סתם *stam* would have been okay. Alright, so that's
I think what you would normally have understood that תנאי בית דין
*tnai Beis Din* somehow is able to frame what my what my
דעת *daas* is. But that's not the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is reading it, and therefore the גמרא *Gemara* takes this as evidence
that a קרבן *korban* even brought without any intent, unless it's actively
wrong intent, without any intent is סתם כשר kasher *stam kosher*. And
as I said, it's very easy to say that by sacrifice because
the whole animal is sanctified and it's an act done to that
animal that has its identity, so it's unless you actively redefine it,
it's the right act. Now we now have to say how do
we know the that that is not true by a גט get,
*get*. Yes?
I mean this is I can't help but think just given where
we are in the cycle of the year, what learning תורה שלא
לשמה lishma *Torah shelo lishmah* then means, can we frame that in
this context? I mean you have the wrong intent or no intent.
There you go, very good, yep. Okay, very
good. Okay, now, לגבי גט get סתמא פסול מנלן *legabei get stama
pasul minalan*. Now, where do we know before we get to your
nice distinction about why they're different, about the logic between it, how
do we know it's true that a גט get, *get*, if you
just have generically writing a name and not thinking about anyone in
particular, how do we know that that's
invalid? Okay, מנלן *minalan*. אילימא מהא
דתנן
היה עובר בשוק ושמע סופרים מקרין *eilima meha detnan haya over bashuk
veshama sofrim makrin* and you were walking through the marketplace and you
were walking by the סופרים *sofrim* school
and
you heard them writing a sample גט *get*. Okay, and the sample
גט *get* was, ראובן בן שמעון *Reuven ben Shimon* divorces שרה בת
רחל *Sarah bas Rachel*. Okay, and you said מקרין איש פלוני גרש
פלונית ממקום פלוני *makrin ish ploni geresh plonis mimakom ploni* and they
did it in Tel Aviv. ואמר *ve'amar* wait, זה שמי וזה שם
אשתי *zeh shemi vezeh shem ishti*. Oh my God, that's my name,
that's my wife's name, we live in Tel Aviv, it's a סימן
מן השמים *siman min hashomayim*, let me go up and I'll go
get buy the גט *get* from them and I'll use it for
my wife. פסול לגרש בו pasul legaresh bo, *pasul legaresh bo*, it's
invalid. Now, that seems to be a great example because they're writing
it for a generic ראובן בן שמעון *Reuven ben Shimon* and שרה
בת רחל *Sarah bas Rachel*. They're not thinking about a wrong woman,
they're just not thinking about the right woman, they're just doing it
for practice. So ואמר *ve'amar* so the גמרא *Gemara* says so you
see that shows you that it's invalid. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
no, דילמא כרב פפא *dilma k'Rav Pappa*, maybe the explanation is not
because it wasn't לשם *leshem* the right woman, but like what רב
פפא *Rav Pappa* says. דאמר רב פפא הכא בסופרין העשויים ללמוד עסקינן
*d'amar Rav Pappa hacha b'sofrin ha'asuyim lilmod askinan*, okay, which is what
was it clear? They're practicing. But because they're practicing, ולא נכתב לשם
כריתות כלל *velo nichtav leshem krisus klal*. It wasn't written it wasn't
written to ever be used as a גט *get*. So that would
show that to be a גט *get*, to write it generically it's
not enough that yes, its identity as a גט *get* has to
be specifically for the purpose of גט *get*. Although why don't you
say that's let's ask that, why is that true by a גט
*get*? Why don't we say סתמא *stama*? But whatever, but we're not
going to say that. So once but once you have it, so
now it's harder to get an example. You can't do a practice
thing because that's ah, that's obviously not good. But what we'd want
to talk about is something that is intentionally being
written as a גט *get* and nevertheless the names are being generic.
How do we know that that's not good? Okay, once its גט
*get* identity has been established. So the גמרא *Gemara* says אלא מהא
ela me-ha *ela meha*, from the following. יתר על כן כתב לגרש
את אשתו ונמלך *yeser al ken kasav legaresh es ishto venimlach*. Goes
further, this is the משנה *Mishnah*. The משנה *Mishnah* just says not
only this is invalid, even this is invalid, even this is invalid.
כתב לגרש את אשתו ונמלך *kasav legaresh es ishto venimlach*, okay, you
wrote this to divorce your wife and then you changed your mind.
So it was written as a גט *get*. ומצאו בן עירו ואמר
לו שמי כשמך ושם אשתי כשם אשתך *umatzau ben iro ve'amar lo
shemi keshimcha veshem ishti keshem ishtecha*. Hey, you know what? We've always
pointed out this curious thing that you and I have the same
names and our wives have the same names. I have a גט
*get* I'm not using. Do you have any interest in it? So
פסול לגרש בו *pasul legaresh bo*, he can't use it. So you
see there it was written for the write of a גט *get*.
But the גמרא *Gemara* says one minute, that the name of the
woman wasn't written generically there. The name of the woman was written
for
man number one's wife. So the גמרא *Gemara* says no, דילמא שאני
התם דאינתק לשם גירושין דההיא *dilma shani hasam d'intek leshem geirushin d'hahi*.
It was specifically designated for that man's wife to be divorced, this
man to divorce his wife and not for this other man. It's
not סתם *stam*. אלא מהא *ela meha*, from the following. יתר על
כן יש לו שתי נשים ששמותיהן שוות *yeser al ken yesh lo
shtei nashim she'shmoseihen shavos*. Guy is married to two, רחל בת שרה
*Rachel bas
Sarah*s.
Okay, not a good idea. כתב לגרש את הגדולה לא יגרש בו
את הקטנה *kasav legaresh es hagedola lo yigaresh bo es haktana*. So
don't if you wrote it for the older one, don't use it
for the younger one. So you see now the answer still is,
is that that's not generic, that's still for particular woman A and
not woman B. דילמא שאני התם דאינתק לשם גירושין דההיא *dilma shani
hasam d'intek leshem geirushin d'hahi*. It was written specifically for that woman's
divorce, not the others. אלא מהא *ela meha*, from the following. יתר
על כן אמר ללבלר כתוב ולמי שארצה אגרש *yeser al ken amar
lelarlar kesov ulmi she'ertzeh agareish*. You say to the לבלר *lavlar* כתוב
*kesov*... Write for just שרה בת רחם, tired of them, one of
them I'm gonna divorce, haven't decided which one, פסול לגרש בו, you
can't use it. So there it's generic and you can't use it
for the
one
even. So the גמרא says no, דילמא שאני התם דאין ברירה, dilma
shani hatam de-ein breira, no, that maybe is because you can't choose,
which is which. Now what does that mean? But who says you
have to choose? So the way רש"י Rashi says it means is,
maybe because what makes that invalid is not its generic nature, but
that if you used it for wife A, I might say but
maybe all along initially you were thinking about wife B. Okay, I
know, so it's not exactly clear why that's true, but since it
wasn't designated and it meant at the very outset was A or
B, you can't use it for A because there was the possibility
of B at the beginning. But so there was still an element
of the wrong woman, not just generic. Okay, אלא מהא from the
following, הכותב טופסי גיטין, hakotev tufsei gittin, if you're writing just the
boilerplate, צריך שיניח מקום האיש ומקום האשה, tzarich she-iniach makom ha-ish u-makom
ha-isha, you have to leave a blank line for the man's name,
the woman's name, ומקום העדים, u-makom ha-edim, the עדים's edim signature, ומקום
הזמן, u-makom ha-zman, and the and the time. ואמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל, ve-amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, אף צריך שיניח מקום הרי את
מותרת לכל אדם, af tzarich she-iniach makom ha-rei at mutereset le-chol adam,
you have to leave blank also the line which is behold you
are permissible to any woman any man, which is what you think
when which you have to have the woman in mind when you're
writing it. But the point that you have to leave it blank
is showing that anything less than anything more I guess that leaving
it blank would be a problem. So even if the names were
written and they were generic and it wasn't thinking about it was
written for the purpose of a גט, but the names somehow were
written and by chance were right, but they were just written generically,
that would be invalid. It's only going to become כשר kasher. if
the line was left blank and it was filled out with that
woman in mind. Okay, so that proves to you that by a
גט you specifically need לשמה lishma and not by a קרבן, and
the difference seems to be not that the different areas of law
require different things. You could just say one thing requires positive לשמה
and the other just require one just say that. One has a
הלכה halacha wrong thoughts invalidate, the other has a הלכה halacha you
need the right thoughts to make it כשר. But we're not saying
it's a difference between what those two legal systems require, you know
areas of law require. It's sort of about the objects that you're
dealing with. When you deal with an object that already has its
identity and been saying to never does it it doesn't really so
much matter what's in your head, it all matters about defining the
act. So when you're dealing with an object that already has its
identity, the act is properly defined unless you actively redefine. If you're
dealing with something like a גט, the object doesn't yet have its
identity, you have to create its identity, so therefore like it's not
valid unless you have the right thing in mind. Okay, so we
will end with this.